Guide to the University of Montana Disability Services for Students Records 1949-1999
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
University of Montana Disability Services for Students records
1949-1999
University of Montana-Missoula Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
RG 090
University of Montana. Disability Services for Students.
0.5 linear feet
This University of Montana Disability Services for Students collection contains correspondence relating to the need for more services and support for students with disabilities. It includes several complaints filed by students as well as internal memos addressing the lack of support for students. This collection is restricted.
Historical Note
Disability Services for Students at the University of Montana in Missoula serves students with disabilities by ensuring that all programs are usable and accessible. In the early 1980s, at the urging of various university departments in response to a bill in the Montana House of Representatives that requested funding for handicapped services for the Commissioner of Higher Education, the University of Montana began exploring options for providing services to its disabled students. A Task Force for Handicapped Services was established with approval from University President Richard Bowers. The task force charged itself with creating a comprehensive list of handicapped students and the services they required as well as determining the cost of such services and possible resources for funding.
In 1988, the Alliance for Disability and Students at the University of Montana (ADSUM) was founded in response to continued access problems for UM students with disabilities. That same year, the University hired Jim Marks as its first disability student advisor to directly oversee students with disabilities and their needs. This position would eventually form the foundation of the Disability Services for Students department at the University of Montana (the first standalone office in support of students with disabilities). By 1989, Jim Marks would be the first coordinator of Disability Services for Students. By 1990, the new office of Disability Services for Students started publishing an official handbook to outline the services available. As of 2015, Disability Services for Students works with individual students to provide reasonable modifications to make programs and facilities accessible.
This collection contains mostly correspondence relating to the need for more services and support for students with disabilities at the University of Montana. It includes several complaints filed by students at the university as well as internal memos addressing the lack of support for students. Two folders are currently restricted along with a letter written by a former student.
Materials are filed topically and arranged chronologically.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula. Due to privacy concerns, some of these materials are restricted; please contact Archives and Special Collections for more details.
These materials were in the possession of their originating office until their donation to Archives and Special Collections in 2015.
Additions to this collection are expected.
Additional materials on early services for students with disabilities are available in the Office of the President of the University of Montana Records (RG 001). Additional publications from Disability Services for Students are available in University Publications at Archives and Special Collections.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
University of Montana--Missoula. Disability Services for Students--Archives; University of Montana--Missoula--Students; Montana State University (Missoula, Mont.); University of Montana (Missoula, Mont.: 1965-1994)
College students with disabilities--Services for--Montana--Missoula
Colleges and Universities; Civil Rights; Montana
- Early Policy and Correspondence -- RESTRICTED, 1949-1977 (Box-folder 2/1)
- Disabled Students Advisor, 1982 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Handicapped Advisory Committee, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Civil Rights Violations at the University of Montana, Complaints and Correspondence -- RESTRICTED, 1988-1990 (Box-folder 2/2)
- University of Montana Evaluation Report, April 1989 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Student Concerns with Retrenchment and Retrenchment Proceedings, June 12, 1989 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Committee Assignments, October 29, 1989 (Box-folder 1/5)
- Communication Sciences and Disorders Services to Disability Services for Students, Retrenchment, 1989 (Box-folder 1/6)
- Auxiliary Services Review, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 1/7)
- Disability Services for Students Communications with Members, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 1/8)
- Retrenchment of Communication Sciences and Disorders Department, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 1/9)
- Campus Development Committee, October 24, 1990 (Box-folder 1/10)
- Bicycles on Campus, Handicapped Access Violations, 1990 (Box-folder 1/11)
- Correspondence, Violations and Services for Students with Disabilities, 1990 (Box-folder 1/12)
- Policies, 1990 (Box-folder 1/13)
- Disability Services for Students Funding Proposal by Alliance for Disability and Students of the University of Montana, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 1/14)
- ADA Compliance Materials, 1996 (Box-folder 1/15)
- ADA Team, 1996-1998 (Box-folder 1/16)
- Alliance for Disability and Students of the University of Montana Complaint, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 1/17)
- University Center Third Floor Renovation, Accessibility, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 1/18)
- Action Plan, May 7, 1999 (Box-folder 1/19)
- Alliance for Disability and Students of the University of Montana Constitution, undated (Box-folder 1/20)